Ira V. Hiscock collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- Other Hiscock materials, Series II
  - Hiscock's Awards
    - "Certificate of Appreciation" from the Mayor of New Haven, Richard C. Lee, and the Board of Health Commissioners, 1958 April 14
    - Honorary Member of the Connecticut Hospital Association, 1971 June 16
    - 1953 Medal of the American Cancer Society, Inc.
      "Presented to Ira V. Hiscock upon the nomination of the Connecticut Division in recognition of his important contributions to the control of cancer."
    - State of California, Department of State, 1939 July
    - C.-E. A. Winslow Award, Connecticut Public Health Association, 1951 May 1
    - Diploma from the Hygienists of Mexico, 1959 October 20
      Large hand-colored decorative parchment, 36.5 x 17 cm., signed in Mexico City by Dr. Jorge Perches Volasco, Dr. Miguel E. Bustamente, and Dr. Germain Selo de la Rea.
- Supplement added 2016
  Custodial History
  The materials in the Supplement were transferred from the Ira V. Hiscock Library (EPH Library) of the Yale School of Public Health. Some were donated to the Ira V. Hiscock Library by Margaret H. Weatherly, Hiscock's daughter, in 1999. Others were donated by Edward DeLouise, Director of the New Haven Department of Public Health, upon his retirement in 1988. He donated "personal letters and materials that Dr. Hiscock sent me over the years." And some of the earlier materials appear to have come from the historical section of the EPH Library, and their provenance is unclear.
  - Public health issues in Westport, Connecticut: Correspondence of Philip E. Nelbach, 1944-1945 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Correspondence of Philip E. Nelbach (Yale College, 1939; M.P.H. Yale, 1938), Assistant Professor of Public Health in the Yale Department of Public Health, with Stanley H. Osborn, Commissioner of Health, State Department of Health, and with Harriet Y. (Mrs. Philip H.) Vivian, head of the Westport Committee for Better Public Health. These letters contain information on the politics of staffing for public health service. Part of the correspondence relates to a bill to form sanitary districts in the state.
  - Newspaper clippings on a community survey of health and welfare agencies in the Greater Hartford area, 1948 November 7-28 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    The survey was: Community Surveys, Inc., Crossroads (An Analytical Study of Health and Welfare services in Greater Hartford, Conn. Hartford: Greater Hartford Community Council, 1948. Hiscock and the Department of Public Health were responsible for the health part of the survey. The newspaper articles in this and the next two folders react to the publication of the survey and its recommendations.
  - Newspaper clippings on a community survey of health and welfare agencies in the Greater Hartford Area: Recreation, 1948 November 14-18 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings on a community survey of health and welfare agencies in the Greater Hartford area: Family and Child Welfare, Public Health, 1948 November 9-20 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Ira Hiscock, "Report on School Health in Taiwan", 1953 June 17 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    "With special reference to participation by the American Bureau of Medical Aid to China." Mimeograph typescript, 6 pages.
  - Poliomyelitis in Connecticut: Materials from the Connecticut State Board of Health, 1955-1960 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Article by Milo Rindge on polio in Connecticut in 1959, especially in New Haven, and mimeograph memoranda by the Connecticut State Department of Health on polio cases and vaccination.
  - Field trip to Greenwich Hospital: Report and printed materials, 1957 March 7 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    The author of the 4-page carbon copy report is not specified. With the report are brochures and forms provided by Greenwich Hospital and Greenwich Health Association.
  - Memoranda on merging Public Health and Epidemiology at Yale, 1957, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    "The Establishment of a Section of Epidemiology at Yale," "Working memorandum produced jointly by the Division of Preventive Medicine and Epidemiology and the Department of Public Health, Yale University, School of Medicine, Draft, 6 June 1957"; "A Proposal for Reorganization of the Program in the Field of Public Health in Yale University," April 7, 1959.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence of Ira V. Hiscock, 1959, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Portrait of Ira V. Hiscock by Deane Keller, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Invitation for the unveiling of the portrait, news release, and photograph of the portrait.
  - "A Half Century of Public Health at Yale" and "After Thoughts", ca. 1965 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    The two documents may not be related but both are about the History of public health at Yale. Neither was dated but Hiscock much later guessed at dates. The second document was about how the building for Epidemiology and Public Health came about.
  - "An Evening with Ira Hiscock," Connecticut Public Health Association, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    From the papers of Edward De Louise, Department of Health, New Haven, who was an organizer of the event held on May 11, 1972.
  - "Extracts of Annual Reports of the Dean in reference to Public Health, with personal note of Ira Hiscock", 1973 November 4 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Contains undated copies of pages on public health from the Dean's reports. Folder includes a photocopy of a 3-page written note by Ira Hiscock on his early career and the first years of the Department of Public Health.
  - Ira V. Hiscock Award of the New England Public Health Association in 1973, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    Issue of the Yankee Crier, "Newsletter of the New England Public Health Association, vol. III, No. 1, Winter 1974, announcing the first Ira V. Hiscock Award given to Professor Clair E. Turner in May 1973. The newsletter contains a supplement: Ira V. Hiscock, "Power for Tomorrow's Health Care and Health Education," a summary of the May 1973 meeting.
  - "The CUP of the Connecticut State Medical Society", 1974 April (Box 8, Folder 15)
    Lunch talk given at the meeting of the C.S.M.S. House of Delegates, New Haven, December 13, 1973. Refers to the Society having conferred on him an honorary M.D. in April 1973. Article was published. See Box 8, Folder 21.
  - Ira V. Hiscock Consumer Award, Connecticut Public Health Association, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    From files of Edward DeLouise. Includes guidelines for the award, two copies of blank award certificates, a photograph of Ira Hiscock with the recipients of the C.-E. A. Winslow award and the first Ira V. Hiscock Award, and a press release about the winners of the 1979 awards with a snapshot of the winners with Edward DeLouise.
  - Correspondence of Ira V. Hiscock with Edward De Louise, 1976-1987 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    These papers are from the files of Edward DeLouise. The folder contains mostly handwritten letters by Hiscock, who was by 1978 living in the Pine Run Community, Doylestown, Pennsylvania. The last letter, in 1987, is from Margaret Hiscock Weatherly saying that her father had died the year before. Included in one of the letters is a photograph of Mrs. Sucher and Mrs. [Anne] Winslow receiving the Winslow award in 1956, sent by Hiscock to DeLouise as an historical piece that might be given to an organization.
  - C.-E. A. Winslow Centenary, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    Illustrated pamphlet by the Department of Epidemiology and Public Health and copy of publication by Arthur J. Viseltear, "C.-E. A. Winslow Day: Proceedings of the June 3, 1977 Centenary Celebration," Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, 50 (1977): 603-630
  - Miscellaneous presentations by Ira V. Hiscock, 1940-1973 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    Five presentations: "Florence Nightingale's Contributions to Public Health," at the Annual Florence Nightingale Service, Norwalk, May 19, 1940; "Whose Job Is It," Annual Meeting of the Oahu Society for Crippled Children and Adults, October 20, 1960; "Health and Medical Care of Children and Youth -- Who Cares?" at Hawaii's White House Conference on Children and Youth, November 17, 1960: Connecticut's Heritage in Health," as President of the Connecticut Public Health Association, October 14, 1973; "Unsung Health Heroes in Connecticut," March 31, 1974. Also, timeline of public health achievements, April 1974.
  - Miscellaneous articles by Ira V. Hiscock, 1927-1974 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1923, 1976-1977 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Articles by Arthur J. Viseltear on the history of public health at Yale, 1977-1988 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Scrapbook of photographs at the opening celebration of the Ira V. Hiscock Library, Department of Epidemiology and Public Heath, 1978 February 3 (Box 9, Item 1)
    Includes the program of the ceremony, signatures of attendees, photographs, and a separate handwritten key to the photographs.
  - Additional copies of photos from the opening of the Ira V. Hiscock Library, 1978 February 3 (Box 9, Item 2)
    Also contains a photo of Ira V. Hiscock, Edward DeLouise, Director of Health, New Haven, and Mayor Frank Logue, New Haven.